hello welcome to voice club welcome to
Bristol where I'm recording this
introduction this was a conversation
actually that was recorded at be on
psychedelics in Prague between myself -
Madeleine
Melissa Warner and Matthew Johnson are
two fantastic people who I'm really
honored to have been able to record
anything with that's all I've got quite
a bit more coming with Melissa actually
she has a wonderful conversation with
Rick Doblin but perhaps it's best if I
introduce and the two of these guys to
you first of all Matthew Matthew is a
PhD and associate professor of
psychiatry at Johns Hopkins University
School of Medicine and a leading expert
on the effects of psychedelics and
really a leading expert he's one of
those people that's published so much
it's like how many rungs above the
average he's right at the top you know
really fantastic energy about him as
well really opening I really enjoyed
meeting him Thank You Matthew for
spending the time again Melissa is very
interesting as well she's a co-founder
of the Australian psychedelic society
board member of prism which is the
Australian equivalent to Maps
it stands for psychedelic research in
science and medicine so really check out
what prism are doing I think it's
important moving forward without further
ado then I bring you Melissa Warner and
Matthew Johnson
you
so I'm with Matthew Johnston today a few
on psychedelics in Prague and Matthew
was an associate professor at John
Hopkins School of Medicine in the USA
and he's been the pioneer of the
research into addiction for the
treatment of psilocybin and also
profiling the nature of mystical States
or peak experience I guess studying
addiction studying the alteration of
consciousness through things like
psychedelics isn't is a way of studying
consciousness and quite curious to know
what is it that led you to have an
interest in the study of consciousness
oh great question great question Melissa
I can come to at that from a number of
different angles one angle is that I
just have a great interest in the
effects of drugs really across all drug
classes whether we're talking about you
know caffeine or cocaine or psilocybin
alcohol you name it and I'm a an
experimental psychologist and really
with a strong emphasis on behavior and
my kind of core foundation even though I
kind of see these as schools of thought
as tools in the toolbox but one of my
core foundations is as a behavioral
psychologist so I I kind of think you
know if you're interested in drugs and
behavior how could you not be interested
in psychedelics and I think in a sense I
think consciousness and in behavior are
two sides of the same coin behavior over
the time reflects consciousness and so
some of the effects of psychedelics are
so profound and are in the domain of
what people call consciousness even
though that you know just the concept
itself is difficult to deal with because
you know people use definitions for what
consciousness is but it these strong
alterations and subjective experience
it's just not uncommon for people to
have an experience on a psychedelic
where they say they could never put it
into words
and that it has profound changes in the
way they think and behave if you're a
psychologist how could you not be
interested in that yeah I think there's
no better way to study the nature of
consciousness than the alteration of it
yeah I I guess the other thing I really
liked what you said there was tools in
the toolbox so I guess that is the tools
to alter consciousness from undesirable
states and there is an array of tools so
state psychedelics are not the only tool
yeah books and what are the conditions
that we're trying to alter in your
research so in terms of problems or
issues that we're trying to help people
with um so one is people dealing with
cancer severe depression or anxiety or
both which is common in cancer and other
potentially terminal disorders so we're
very interested in that we conducted a
very promising trial and published it
about a year ago hoping to do a much
larger study that might with colleagues
at a number of sites that would gain
approval for the you know non research
just straight-up therapeutic use of
psilocybin and then another one the
other major therapeutic area that we're
looking at is in the treatment of
addiction specifically cigarette smoking
people who have tried multiple times to
quit and have not been able to but I
should say also the the foundation of
our work and the initial studies that
our group has done at Johns Hopkins or
in people without any kind of diagnosis
disorders but of course we're all human
beings and there's always things that
can be improved the the betterment of
well people the kind of if you would
self actualization
positive psychology you know in that
spirit I think our original research
with those healthy normals we're seeing
some the basic phenomena that we
observed in those we see them in these
therapeutic populations and in fact we
see mechanistically similarities such as
the important mediating role of the
mystical experience at the certain type
of subjective experience after taking
psilocybin not just taking psilocybin so
it's predictive of better outcomes for
just regular old people healthy people
reporting improvements in their life and
their attitudes and behaviors but also
mystical experience being tied to more
likely being still abstinent from
smoking once down the road after trying
to quit and also having less anxiety and
depression yes so much so much to go
with there and it's one of there's a
theme that I sort of observed there with
end-of-life anxiety addiction there's a
mood a sense of movement there's a
there's a shift in someone's life that
is occurring and it's a matter of trying
to deal with that
whereas addiction is being stuck
somewhere so there's something about a D
habituation would you say yeah I I think
that I think actually D habituation is a
great term in fact that that that's
similar to some of the language that
that Tim Leary used in talking about
these agents which I think we we should
return to I'm interested in you know
really looking at these effects as as
learning trials as conditioning I think
there's something like D habituation
that's going on but I would say I I sort
of hold that as going on not just with
the addiction treatment but also with
with the cancer distress and anxiety and
presumably with the research that the
Imperial group published with straight
up depression patient patients you know
outside of a cancer context and we're
currently doing a pilot study with
straight-up depression patients right
now but I think that you know yes it's a
big shift in their life that kind of got
them you know the diagnosis of cancer
that got them
to this place but I think they too are
stuck and so whether you're stuck you're
sort of stuck in this narrow pattern of
behavior when it comes to addiction you
know I'm a smoker oh gosh I've relapsed
again I've tried a million times
I'm never gonna be successful I'm just a
smoker you know being stuck in this loop
or in how you're dealing with cancer
like I deserve this you know
why me you know this is this great
punishment I am you know you know some
people you know come and think you know
holding this kind of judgment that God
is punishing them or just some other
kind of narrative for people that
medically can have right now a very full
life they're not having a full life not
because of the straight-up medical
consequences of their cancer but because
of that narrow thinking that it's the
cancer diagnosis has led them to so I
view that as very similar between you
know drug addictions or this sort of
addiction to thinking of you of yourself
your life in this certain way yeah
absolutely a negative self story exactly
it's just a repeating thing that that
someone can't really get out of and it's
such a phenomenally restrictive thing as
well like it's it's a real affect ation
to be in that place you know you're
really you're really contending with it
so so here I'm gonna scramble around
here I had a question but but it's to do
with mystical experience and to do with
the fact that we know that when the
mystical experience does occur you know
in these therapeutic sessions that is
correlated with much better outcomes
which is really really fascinating and
you could talk about it from so many
different ways but I just I'd be really
interested to hear your thoughts on how
you've
recognized you know your patients be
able to set like what kind of story can
they can they can they move towards you
know is there is there a resetting of
some some underlying goal that happens
it's kind of a breakthrough from the
negative self story open to the world or
open to a different way you can be in it
there's a there's a breakthrough that
kind of happens there and I'm
particularly interested in for people
who might not have had psychedelics
right and who might not have access to
them like I'm interested in how we might
describe what it feels like to imagine
how to be in a different way and that
kind of acts in some unconscious and
really fundamental way as I can a new
landscape you can live in and be part of
you know I know I'm throwing things at
you here but could you talk to could you
talk to how someone who might not have
had a mystical experience before could
grip onto how their whole conception of
themselves and what it is to feel like
to be then can change sure I think a
good analogy which is very salient for
me right now being in the Czech Republic
from the United States is travel in
Michael Pollan I believe makes this
point in his recent book about
psychedelics and I think it's a great
point great analogy Travel introduces
you it Ramon
it makes the million things that you're
habituated to in life that you you don't
even recognize their influence and all
of a sudden you're aware of them like I
don't know how to open this door I don't
know how they're like this you know
appliance works you know it's light and
you take a second to figure that and
just you know like or if you're in
London and everyone's going up on the
left side of this stairwell just like
when they're driving inside you notice
these things and you just you don't
notice that when you're you're back home
and everyone's just doing their thing
and you are reminded of how much of
life and circumstances that we just skip
over that we rely on heuristics and the
older we are as human beings the more we
rely on these heuristics and that's
important in that those heuristics are
part of wisdom that hopefully we develop
over time but it can also lock us in a
certain way of thinking and not even
recognizing just that initial
recognition that there is another way
and I think some of the most dramatic
experiences are like that where what
they kind of break through to might
differ for the individual whether it be
more connection with their family more
of a perspective of other people in
their lives more of a sympathetic view
of themselves a lot of people they would
take far more compassion on someone else
if they were from an extra right
perspective right or sometimes we've had
many patients and area studies returning
to things that they did they say yeah I
wrote you know a 50-year old woman said
you know like I was really into poetry
in college I haven't written poetry in
decades and like I love poetry why am I
writing poets they start writing poetry
again you know yeah it's it's it's very
interesting when I said do you have
things of the situation of the mind of
allowing people to enter transition into
their lives I'm curious about the the
other tools in the toolbox and how your
research into meditation relates to
psychedelics because meditation is
another way at habituating the minds of
practice and it's been reliably shown to
have some similar effects in the brain
to psychedelics and but I'm curious
about how these two can combine because
you know meditation is hard particularly
for somebody who is suffering from
mental illness or who is suffering from
addiction
it's it's a it's a it's a practice that
you have to curate over a decent amount
of time to be able to get the rewards
out of and what what I know you have
been doing researchers into the
combination of using psilocybin with
meditation and if with experienced
meditators is that correct
we've
we've finished and published a study
with novice meditators 75 folks that
type of folks like a lot of people say
oh I've always kind of been interested
and I've tried a few times over the
years I can never quite stick to it but
it reveals wall and were we haven't
finished it yet but we've been working
with in this new study long term
meditators people with any number of you
know some you know five ten thousand
hours of meditation over their lifetime
sort of looking at a broad number of
questions of how that might impact their
current practice whether they get more
out of their practice and on all of
these questions we of course look at
both sides of the coin maybe they're
maybe it hurts their practice these
types of things in the novice meditators
something we can speak to you know the
results of we saw a clear signal of of
an additive effect on various measures
such as altruism improvements and in
quality of life engagement and spiritual
practices and sort of reaping the
benefits of spiritual practice we
essentially found that whether you had
sort of in a really heavy dose of a
spiritual practice support so having not
just having the psilocybin session and
not just having kind of our standard in
what we think is minimal for safety
preparation and then follow-up
integration for this high support group
that we included in this study these
these people had extra integration
sessions and they they were able to do
something really cool that we haven't
done in other studies we actually have
our subjects formally get together in
discussion groups and share their
experiences with each other and have
mutual support what some of the
experiences of the participants well
there are a large number of participants
really though I would say in terms of
the the core experience it was very
similar to our the research you know
strong high rates of mystical experience
defined by these criteria of a strong
sense of unity a sense of positivity
there's a sort of a noetic quality which
first assume this like self-revealing
quality somehow it's more real than real
and a sense that it's the experience is
so profound it's it's beyond words and
we actually found that an one group had
just a kind of a trivial dose of
psilocybin kind of serving as a placebo
and you know getting just even if you're
in the standard support group without
that kind of extra heavy dose of
integration and the discussion groups
that you know just having the high dose
of psilocybin even without that extra
support
you know you that was what we was
responsible for having high rates of
mystical experience but then in terms of
the fruits of that mystical experience
how do you know question how does that
mystical experience translate into
improvements in your life so we don't
want just all these states we want holds
it traits yes and this is very much in
the spirit of Houston Smith who talked
about and wrote about this that you know
mystical experiences are one thing but
you know spiritual experiences
I mean spiritual and meditation work I
know that it's a bit of a hot word for
some people particularly from a
scientific background and so with with
meditation I'm curious to know all of
the some measures in what kind of
cognitive change were you looking for
things like no non reactivity acceptance
a sense of meaning things like that just
to break down the word what spiritual is
referring to here and the other thing
was is in in this group so I'm curious
because meditation has an ability to
allow you to navigate your mind with
greater ease was there a difference in
the meditative group with their ease of
the psilocybin experience yes yes so
make sure I understand you correctly did
they well I'll say in our long-term
meditators folks have said that they can
slip
into the met in different states more
readily and and there's some variation
some folks say that they can get more
out of a shorter time of meditation now
and interestingly I think some folks
seem to take their meditation less
compulsively so in one sense this might
sound odd but one can kind of think of
meditation as being stuck in a rut I
mean there are folks that can you know
be you know if you don't get your want
you know one hour or sometimes several
hours of meditation in every day you
feel like if you failed you know and you
know not allowing cutting yourself any
slack you know like you've you know but
you're traveling or something in you
know flight more flexibility thank you
that's a great way to put it more
flexibility in their meditative practice
and the regularly in the other areas of
their life too yeah in in some sense of
a common a story we've heard is that
just an increased recognition that it's
not about the practice it's about where
you get with the practice and so you
know you may not need that practice to
that degree all the time yeah it
requires an engagement with the world
mm-hmm I think that's another
interesting thing about psychedelics and
the mystical experience with a peak
experience is this sense of awe and
wonder at the world which participants
frequently report yeah this orientation
away from the internal self to the the
Wonder and the majesty of what is out
there yeah and an engagement with that
can you speak to that effect yeah that
and in fact I'd point folks to a recent
but soon to be published paper by our
colleague at the University of Alabama
Birmingham Peter Hendrix has a paper
titled I think all as antidote
you know postulating that awe is maybe
an under-recognized
construct at play here with these you
know therapeutic and the betterment of
well people effects of psychedelics this
this idea of
through you know pharmacology or or
whatever other means confronted with
something so much larger than oneself
that the the sense of self and sort of
the problems that can come along with
the sense of self-identity
can be helped and whether that's kind of
staring out before the Grand Canyon or
maybe you know 30 min 30 milligrams of
psilocybin running through your your
blood you can lead to these profound
experiences of all so I think that's I
think there's a lot to that and and
that's closely associated with the
mystical experience any of use the term
peak experience a few times and I should
say those may be completely synonymous
concepts that are described slightly do
that's kind of my working assumption or
they might be slightly different shades
of the same phenomenon I feel like
they're the same thing to just defined
by different groups or different people
Abraham Maslow defining peak experience
and I believe mystical experience was
defined along with like the world of
Pankey experiment using psilocybin in
earlier before the laws the change in
earlier folks Walter's space and even
William James you know were kind of
focused on this construct but yeah the
in terms of really making progress and
understanding with psychedelics yeah
Wally panky and and Bill Richards in our
group made great contributions there
yeah I mean we don't have too long left
so perhaps my final question would just
be so what drives you to be interested
in doing this mm-hmm you know and I'll
leave that broad yeah I can I can come
at that at a number of directions I
guess from one perspective I kind of
think um you know what is meaningful in
my life like what am i I'm only gonna be
around a little while I mean I'm I'm 44
like you know I do have I might be
you're a slightly 44 some folks do my
20s and might be like I said
finish college when I was 10 years old
but now I'm nothing nothing like that
but you know you know and I'm involved
with a variety of research topics beyond
psychedelics but I really see
psychedelics as something that can doing
this work can really contribute to the
to the health of humanity I think we're
getting to it let me preface it by
saying I think there can be a danger and
in speaking to largely about this yes
and it's not a panacea it's I'm
certainly not saying everyone should use
psychedelics but we are dealing with
constructs that I think are really
important and in psychedelics is perhaps
just one way but the topics that we're
dealing with this sense of unity that we
are all ultimately a part of something
that is beyond ourselves and that we are
all ultimately completely interconnected
like we're all ultimately on this little
rock in the middle of space and we're
all we have all right each other if we
don't really get that broadly you know
our species is in trouble and I think
we're at the time in the history of
humanity where and I don't know whether
it's the next five years 20 years 100
years but it's a blink of an eye in
terms of history but we're there right
now and you know being someone who has
training and behavior in pharmacology
studying psychedelics is one way that I
can contribute to something that I think
is meaningful in terms of hopefully
helping us get through this period I
think we're we're either gonna make it
or not you know are we gonna be around
in a thousand years and what'swhat's the
nature I know this is a really big
picture and I don't want to see this is
the only thing in that category in fact
it may be ultimately be a minor player
but something it's an area that I can
contribute to in that larger picture no
absolutely well I mean psilocybin the
the compound is obviously a minor player
at some level but but the mystical
experience the feeling of connection
right opening up to something new okay
seeing the world
in a way you didn't see it before in a
way that that has at least the belief
that there is a good that you can be a
part of with it that there's a life
there that there's a vitality you can
tap into that that same sense of
vitality is ultimately what grounds
relationships between all individuals of
any group you know I think it is you
know there's a there's many different
ways to to open what you are
authentically into a real relationship
with someone else and the world and
psychedelics administered properly with
the due amount of serious intent you
know and depends what we mean by serious
seems to be a way that certain people
can get them and then also in their
lives at at helping others to
participate in that same kind of sharing
and experience but I know we do have to
wrap up Melissa thank you so much for
being with me doing this thanks to both
you Melissa and Matthew as well so thank
you very much everybody for being here
we'll see you soon
[Music]
you